<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the king at White-hall on the fifth of November, 1681 by George Hooper ...</title>
            <author>Hooper, George, 1640-1727.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R228742</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12254122</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12254122</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57271</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44415)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57271)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 149:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the king at White-hall on the fifth of November, 1681 by George Hooper ...</title>
                  <author>Hooper, George, 1640-1727.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Mark Pardoe ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Printed by His Majesties command"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacks p. 1-4.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXII, 21 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57271:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57271:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the KING AT WHITE-HALL, ON THE <hi>Fifth of November,</hi> 1681.</p>
            <p>By GEORGE HOOPER, D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by his Majeſties Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Mark Pardoe</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Black-Raven</hi> over againſt <hi>Bedford</hi> Houſe in the <hi>Strand,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:57271:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57271:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>S. MATTHEW 22.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Render therefore unto Caeſar, the Things that are <hi>Caeſar's;</hi> and unto God, the Things that are God's.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Phariſees and the Sadduces, though di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in their Opinions and their Intereſts, yet both looking upon our Saviour as their common enemy (he equally oppoſing the Impiety of the one, and the Hypocriſie of the other) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire together <hi>to entangle him in his talk;</hi> and make here in this Chapter their ſucceſſive attempts upon him.</p>
            <p>THe firſt, that of the Phariſees, and which gave an occaſion to the reply of the Text, was manag'd with addreſs and deſign: they had ſo laid their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh, that which way ſoever he took, he might fall into the Snare and periſh; the anſwer he gave, they expected, would certainly offend either the Zeal of the Jew, or the Power of the Roman.</p>
            <p>For the Jews, although they had now for a long while been under ſubjection to the uncircumciſed; although their Great City had been ruin'd by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57271:3"/>Babylonian, and their whole Nation tranſplanted, hardly a Stone left upon a Stone, nor a Jew in <hi>Judea;</hi> though, after their return from their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, they were ſtill Vaſſals to the Perſian Empire, then part of the Conqueſt of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, after under the Syrian Kings, then reduc'd to the Roman Obedience by <hi>Pompey;</hi> (for their Chiefs, whether Princes or Prieſts, were ſtill tributary and dependant;) yet they ſtill retain'd their high Spirit, a peculiar ſence of their Native Liberty and Sacred Prerogatives. But when afterwards the Romans took the Government into their own hands, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd their Tetrarch, and brought them into the condition of a Province, to be commanded now by one ſent from <hi>Rome,</hi> who ſhould have the Power of Life and Death, and Tax them at his will; this ſeem'd inſupportable to the greateſt part of them, and was eſteem'd as unlawful as it was burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome: that they were a holy People; their Perſons and Eſtates ſacred to God; and to give Obedience to any Forreigner, was to withdraw it from the Lord of Hoſts. Nor ſhall we think it was any hard matter, to perſwade a People ſo well ſatisfied of their National Priviledges, and of ſo ſtubborn a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that it was an ungodly thing to ſuffer Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to pay Taxes was Irreligion. He then that reſiſted this Heathen Authority, was the trueſt Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite; the trueſt to the Liberty of his Nation, and the honour of his God; and as <hi>Moſes</hi> had deliver'd them from the Egyptian Bondage, ſo they expected a Meſſiah, who ſhould redeem them from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: and if our Saviour pretended to be that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57271:3"/>great Perſon; he was, they thought, oblig'd to take this Yoke from off their Necks, and declare againſt the Roman Government.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide the Romans knowing what People they had to deal with; that they were a rebellious City, hurtful unto Kings, and unto Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, which would pay neither Toll, Tribute, nor Cuſtom; for ſo they ſtand of old deſcrib'd to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes;</hi> had a very watchful Eye over them, and were jealous of every Motion: They had their Spyes, the Herodians here in the Text; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained their unquiet tumultuous Spirits, with ſevere exemplary Executions. So that to accuſe one of a Crime againſt the State, as an Enemy to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> was the greateſt Revenge the moſt malicious Enemy could take; it was to expoſe him to certain Ruine, to an ignominious cruel Death. For ſo we find the Chief Prieſts, when they had taken Counſel together, to put Jeſus to Death for Crimes, as they thought, againſt their Law; yet preſenting him to <hi>Pilate</hi> with this Accuſation. <hi>We found this Man pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the People, forbidding to give Tribute to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>ſaying that he himſelf, is Chriſt a King.</hi> We have them therefore here preparing that Article, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hereafter they intend to murder him. They indeavour now, by the Queſtion they maliciouſly propoſe, <hi>to take ſuch hold of his Words, that they may deliver him over to the Power and Authority of the Governour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Diſciples therefore of the Phariſees, who poſſibly were againſt the payment of Tribute, and the Herodians who were for it, being both here met
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57271:4"/>together, the one to tempt, and the other to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form; begin their Diſcourſe to him with this flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering treacherous Inſinuation: <hi>Maſter, We know that thou art true, and teacheſt the Word of God in Truth, neither careſt thou for any Man; for thou regardeſt not the Perſon of Men:</hi> thou art not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of the Government, and wilt not for fear diſguiſe the Truth, as our Scribes and our Doctors do. <hi>Tell us therefore, what thinkeſt thou? Is it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to give Tribute to</hi> Caeſar <hi>or not? But Jeſus,</hi> as the Text proceeds, <hi>perceived their Wickedneſs, and ſaid, why tempt ye me Hypocrites? Shew me the Tribute Money, and they brought unto him a Penny; and he ſaith unto them, whoſe is this Image and Superſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? And they ſay unto him</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s; then ſaith he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them,</hi> returning them a preciſe diſtinct Anſwer, and no other than what they themſelves had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced: <hi>Render therefore unto</hi> Caeſar, <hi>the things which are</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s; and unto God, the things that are God's.</hi> The Soveraignty of <hi>Caeſar</hi> over you appears by his Prerogative of coyning your Money: You know your Governour, for you ſee his Face; and in the Inſcription, you read his Authority. Why there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould you deny him the Teſtimony of your Subjection, and refuſe to pay him Tribute? His Stamp I ſee is current with you, is the regulation of your Contract, the Standard of your civil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce: And, as in Payments, you can't refuſe to accept it, ſo here you are obliged to give it. If <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> be your King, this Payment he asks, is as due as any you demand: and that he is your Prince, the Money, you would withhold, of it ſelf teſtifies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57271:4"/>you. God does not here interpoſe any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Claim; nor will he lend his Name to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance your Diſobedience againſt your King, and his Vicegerent. If indeed he ſets up his Image in the Temple, you are not to ſuffer it for God's ſake; and if he commands you to worſhip This, you are not to obey him: but to give It in Tribute is your Duty; it is that which God does ſo far not forbid, that he does command: <hi>Give therefore unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s, and unto God, the things that are God's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Words of our Saviour relate indeed to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Queſtion, and chiefly there concern the giving of Tribute; but they are too the Foundation of a general Rule, and determine alike in all matters, that can come in diſpute betwixt God's Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and that which is delegated to the Sons of Men. They importing, that ſome things there are peculiarly belonging to God, and ſome things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the King; and, whoſe they are, we may know by the Inſcription.</p>
            <p>And this Determination we ſhall crave leave to proſecute, that way the occaſion of the Day leads: by repreſenting, Firſt, the Rights of God, and of <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Secondly, the Uſurpations of the Pope upon both; and Thirdly, the Redreſs and Reform.</p>
            <p>The Rights of God, and the King, and the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57271:5"/>the See of <hi>Rome</hi> has committed upon both, have been made ſo evident by others, that they will need here but a very brief Recapitulation.</p>
            <p n="1">Firſt, If we enquire what is God's, we are to conſider him as Lord in chief, and ſole Proprietor, whoſe is the World, and all that dwell therein. Part indeed of his Dominion, he hath been pleaſed to beſtow on the Sons of Men; but ſo as to be held of him, by ſuch Laws, with ſuch Services, and under ſuch Reſervations, as it ſhall have pleaſed the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Donor.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He has therefore reſerv'd to himſelf the power of declaring Laws, and thoſe not to be overrul'd, nor ſuperſeded, but by himſelf; to bind every where, and for ever; to paſs through all Countries, and continue to all Ages. And thoſe you may read: he has delivered them in Writing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He has accordingly preſcribed the Worſhip that ſhall be paid him, and the Services he expects. Thoſe that are peculiar to him have his Image, his Mark ſet upon them, and are Incommunicable. For he is a jealous God, and will not give his Honour to another.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And for this peculiar Service, he has choſen to be waited upon by a diſtinct peculiar People; that the Homage and Worſhip of the World may be preſented to him in publick, by proper hallowed Hands. And theſe Men, they too have their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57271:5"/>you may know them whoſe they are, and to whom they belong.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the laſt place we may mention as proper to God, not what he has primarily reſerved, but what afterwards his pious Servants out of Zeal and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude have offered to him. Such are all Donations ſacred to his Name, and appropriated to his Service. Theſe Poſſeſſions and Revenues, whoſe they are, you will find too by their Inſcription; look into the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of their Foundations, and you will ſee: they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to God.</p>
            <p>In the next place conſider we what is <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s: and if we look upon him, we ſhall know his Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and his Value. Whoſe Image bears he? And whom does he repreſent? Is he not the Vicegerent of God?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Wherever therefore his Sovereign, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, has not prevented him by any precedent Commands, there he has right and liberty to put forth his: in thoſe caſes to expect an active cheerful Obedience; and that we ſhould in no caſe, and for no reaſon, reſiſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be this Civil Government, Heretick or Infidel, we are not diſcharged of our Allegiance. We are obliged by the ſame Divine Authority to preſerve our Religion under it, and to continue to it our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. Nor are any Modern Governours of the Church greater than their Fathers the Apoſtles;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57271:6"/>who obey'd patiently the worſt of Heathen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; ſubmitting either to their Edicts, or Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Duty of the Chriſtian Emperor being to reſtrain Vice and Irreligion, to promote Holineſs, and the Worſhip of God; to him it belongs to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and direct the Church, the way he ſhall think moſt proper for thoſe ends; to be its Temporal O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeer.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the unqueſtionable Rights of the Civil Power, affirm'd in our Articles, and aſſerted at large by others; and to be given up to it, by thoſe that will render to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> what is <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Neither are the Rights of God and the King more evident, than that the Pope has invaded both. His Uſurpations are now grown as conſpicuous as his Greatneſs; and to recount them all, would be to give a particular of his whole Authority.</p>
            <p>Every one knows, his Principality over the other Churches of the World, what an unjuſt Claim it is, and how meanly founded. How his Authority at firſt was no greater than that of his Neighbour Biſhops; the Style the ſame, and his Holyneſs in common: His Precedence not in the Right of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> but of a Capital City; and Addreſſes firſt made to him, not becauſe he was next to God, but to the Imperial Court. How from the civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Precedence they claim'd a Superiority; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had been conſulted with, they would af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57271:6"/>command: from arbitrating of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence referred to them by their Brethren concern'd, they uſurp'd a Judicature: and then, when none durſt contradict them, they could not err, and grew Infallible.</p>
            <p>It is too as well known, how taking advantage of the weakneſs of an old Empire, and making ſtill conditions with the new; authorizing the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpations of others in countenance to their own; abuſing to their private purpoſes the zealous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of new converted Barbarians, and impoſing on their unlearn'd Simplicity by the Authority of forg'd Donations and counterfeit Decretals; and having before by various Arts, and thorough the connivence or aſſiſtance of Princes, gained an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power over the Biſhops of the Weſt; They then, by the aid of the enſlaved Clergy, and their Garriſons of Monks, attempted openly on the Princes themſelves: confined their Juriſdiction; and forbid them to meddle with the Perſons or Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of Eccleſiaſticks: Authoritatively interpos'd in all Differences, between Prince and Prince, or Prince and People; with their Spiritual Thunder in their hands, commanded the World to lay down, or take up Arms at their Pleaſure: exerciſing every where by their Legates the Sovereign Power of Peace and War; giving the Law, and diſpoſing of Crowns and Lands as they thought fit. He that diſobey'd was firſt thrown out of the Church, and then out of his Country; his Subjects abſolv'd from their Allegiance; and thoſe juſtified that had a mind to rebel or to invade. They did the Holy Church and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57271:7"/>Saint <hi>Peter</hi> Service, that ſeiz'd upon his Eſtate or his Perſon: He ſtood delivered up to Satan, to be Buffeted on Earth, and Tormented in Hell.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Steps to the Papal Throne; and when they were mounted, ſo have they Lorded it; trampling imperiouſly on the Necks of Kings and Biſhops in an equal violation of all Authority Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and Civil. They are the firſt that directed pretended Holy Orders of men, and Sons of Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in Separate Congregations, to deſpiſe their true Spiritual Governours: and firſt inſtructed Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Subjects, to rebel againſt their King, the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified way.</p>
            <p>And theſe Injuſtices of their Growth, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences of their grown Power, lie ſo open in the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Annals of the Chriſtian Times; That, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their Cauſe, they have reaſon to forbid the reading of all Hiſtories, as well as of the Holy Bible. There we may as eaſily diſcern the beginning, and gradual advance of the aſpiring Papacy, as of any other uſurping Empire: and that this new <hi>Rome</hi> has, by means, as humane as thoſe the Old practiſed, and with as little of divine Right extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the narrowneſs of its original Territory, into a Catholick Dominion. And there we ſhall find, as ſoon as it riſes to its plenitude of Power, nothing but Robbery and Cruelty; the World in a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Diſturbance, by Interdicts and Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; all the Wars and Confuſions of whole A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, commanded and managed by this unchriſtian Authority: Emperors at their Feet; kickt away; depoſed by them, to be murdered by their Subjects,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57271:7"/>and their Sons: The Crowns of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> given away on any diſtaſt; as if thoſe Princes had been only Vicars of the Church; and at beſt (what they forced one of ours to own) but Homagers to the Holy See.</p>
            <p>This Uſage, on all occaſions, Crown'd Heads of their own Communion have felt from their Holy Father. But, if the Crime the Pope charg'd bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd on Hereſie; Then the Thunderbolts flew, and the World was to Tremble: to invade that Prince was like a Journey againſt Infidels; to ſtab him me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious; and the Aſſaſſin to be Canoniz'd: and ſo in the laſt Age, on the Preſumption of ſuch a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, dyed <hi>Henry</hi> the Third of <hi>France:</hi> The vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lainous Murderer in open Conſiſtory recognized by the Pope for a Religious <hi>Hero;</hi> and the Relief of <hi>Paris,</hi> by ſuch an ungodly Fact, compared with the Redemption of Mankind. Under the ſame Danger, by a more expreſs Decree, lay <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth his Succeſſor: till he ſuffered himſelf to be Inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, how he might be ſafe from the Maſter of the Aſſaſſins, the Old Man of the Mountains; and laid down his Conſcience at the Pope's Feet, to hold his Life and his Crown.</p>
            <p>And, not to mention their impotent Fury againſt our <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, their Former Defender; by the ſame Authority, and with as little effect, did four of that See ſucceſſively thunder againſt our late Glorious Queen; and ſolemnly declare her depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of her Kingdoms. As they had deprived her of thoſe and her Life; if God would have ſuffered private Treachery, open Rebellion, or a Forrain Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57271:8"/>Invaſion to ſucceed. And in conſequence of ſuch a Declaration made by the laſt of them, and with as much Juſtice, was the Traiterous Attempt made, we this day remember; and King <hi>James</hi> of Bleſſed Memory, and the three Eſtates of the Realm together, condemned to one Fire.</p>
            <p>So do they give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> his Due. And what then can Heretical Subjects expect? they are to fall by thouſands, ſelf-condemn'd, and without the Honourable Ceremony of a Bull: to be ſlaughter'd, like Sheep abandoned by the angry Shepherd; as in the Butchery of <hi>Paris,</hi> or by the Wolves of <hi>Ireland.</hi> For Mercy is not the due of a Heretick; nor has he right to common Faith: his Life belongs not to him.</p>
            <p>But how is it that the great Spiritual Father deals with his obedient Children? Does he not ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them their due? He, like an Old Roman Father, treats them with an unaccountable Power: allows them no Propriety; and denies them the uſe of all that their good God had given them.</p>
            <p>He takes out of their Hands the Holy Scriptures, the greateſt Gift of the Holy Ghoſt; their only Comfort, and Inſtruction. And inſtead of it puts a Legend; for the Word of Life and Truth, unedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying fabulous Traditions: for Bread, a Stone; for Fiſh a Serpent. If that See had pretended but a little earlier Power over the Bleſſed Spirit, they might have commanded it not to write: however now they forbid the People to read.</p>
            <p>He keeps from them the Legacy of their dying Saviour: one half, of the ſpiritual Nouriſhment bequeathed them.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:57271:8"/>
            <p>He denys them the uſe of their Underſtandings and Judgements, in almoſt all the Articles of their Faith: of their Sences too, in that of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</p>
            <p>He takes from them the knowledg of the Prayers, offered in their Name: and lets them not underſtand their own Deſires. So are the People to appear before God, dumb and Senſeleſs; like one of their Idols. All is to be referred to the Prieſt; The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of their Sins, is to depend on his Diſcretion: and the Efficacy of that part of the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is left, on the Sincerity of his Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>So is man robbed of his Spiritual Conſolation: and the good God of his gracious Purpoſes. But they are more bold yet with the Almighty.</p>
            <p>That Princes may not complain of reſpect of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; they abſolve, in ſome Caſes, from the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of God himſelf; and avowedly allow, what he as poſitively forbids: authoriſe inceſtuous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions, and licenſe Perjury: paſs Pardons for all Sins, committed againſt the Divine Majeſty.</p>
            <p>They make the Authority of the Writings of God, to depend upon their own: and add to them as they ſee cauſe; creating new Articles of Faith, and Inſtituting almoſt a new Religion.</p>
            <p>They give away his Worſhip: make their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouteſt Addreſſes, and pay their moſt humble ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments, to the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> to Angels, to Favourite Saints. And, that there may not be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rivals with our God,</p>
            <p>They create Saints; give Crowns above, as well
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57271:9"/>as below: and diſpoſe of Heaven as their own.</p>
            <p>They give Divine Honour to Bread; which they call a God: and to an Image; which to the Eye they might better Tranſubſtantiate.</p>
            <p>And, to cover their Idolatry, they commit Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege, ſteal away one of the ten Commandements; and by their <hi>Index Expurgatorius</hi> blot the two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles themſelves.</p>
            <p>So far has the Papal See been from obſerving the Rule of the Text; from giving to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> what is <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s; or to God, what is God's.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Church, of which we have the Bleſſing to be Members, and whoſe Preſervation we more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly acknowledge this Day, with Thanks to God Almighty its Defendor, appears in its refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, to have propoſed to it ſelf, this Rule of our Saviour's: to have had in it no other Deſign, than by a juſt and equal diſtribution to give to God, what is God's; and to Man, what is Man's. It has ſurveyed the ſeveral Claims in the name of God and of the King; has conſidered whoſe peculiar Stamp and Character thoſe things, that were challenged, bore; and has reſtored them, by the direction of thoſe Marks, to their rightful Proprietors. In this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of Rights, and general Reſtitution, it has not minded any Intereſt of its own; nor laid its Hands on what belongs not to it: It has not had any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Deſign, to gain by what it was to diſtribute: It has ſtood upright, and held the Ballance ſteady; dealing to each their own, ingenuouſly, and with an impartial Hand.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:57271:9"/>
            <p>To God, as is moſt due, it renders firſt his own, to his Perſon, a Worſhip intirely Divine; an Honour not before leſſened on any rival part of his Creation: to his Laws, an Obedience, which no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Command ſhall controle, nor Diſpenſation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe.</p>
            <p>To Princes next, and thoſe that are in Authority, it has reſtored the full exerciſe of their lawful Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: their Countries, and their People, again their own; no place privileg'd, nor Perſon exempted; no forain Potentate ſharing the Authority, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding the Revenue; their Subjects bound in an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, not to be withdrawn on any Pretence, of Schiſm or Hereſie; in the Power of no Conſiſtory to diſcharge.</p>
            <p>And here we ſee no Politick reſerve: that our Church has not provided for it ſelf any other Refuge, but in the Providence of God, and the Piety of the Civil Power. What was not her own, ſhe has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out of her Hands: where ſhe can't communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, yet there ſhe will obey; and where ſhe can't obey, ſhe is ready to endure; expecting her Reward in Heaven. Not ignorant, how much ſhe ſuffers now from the Contradiction of diſloyal Men, for the Truth of this Doctrine, and how much by its meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſhe ſtands expoſed to future Perſecution; yet ſhe profeſſes to know too, that her Saviour's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is not of this World: that the Rendezvous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Prince is not protected by being in a Church: turns not her Congregations into Armies. That the Sword is joyned with the Keys; and that Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication is armed with any civil Penalties; It
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57271:10"/>acknowledges to be, from the Care and Authority of the Civil Government: that thence it has its tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Power over Subjects; ſo far is it from aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any over the Superiors themſelves. And, tho parties, ſeemingly oppoſite, agree in the contrary Opinion; we take not that for an Argument of its Truth: equally deteſting the Holy League of the one, and, the Solemn League of the other.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Caeſar</hi> be Heathen, and like him in the Text; ſo far our Church obeyes: If he profeſſes the Faith, and ſhe finds him in her Aſſemblies; ſhe gives him as his own, the ſupreme Direction and Guidance of eccleſiaſtick Affairs, to ſettle its outward Policy, and be its Moderator and Governour. And yet gives not ſo much, as to take away from the Ordination of God. Her Miniſters act under his Protection: but in vertue of a Commiſſion from above; of an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſpiritual, and derived by other Hands.</p>
            <p>So far hath the Church of <hi>England</hi> been from op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, or flattering the Civil Power; neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting its ſelf againſt the Prince, nor the Prince a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God: in a conſtant Uniform Practice of this Rule of the Text: <hi>Giving to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>what is</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s; and to God what is God's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſame temper, and with the ſame impartia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, ſhe has endeavoured to reduce all things to their antient Limits; and render to every one their Due. Arrogates not to her ſelf an Infallibility in her decrees: but permits to every private Perſon to judge, and Conſider: and yet authoriſes not a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton giddy Spirit, a Judgment without Diſcretion; but adviſes the unlearned to attend to thoſe that are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57271:10"/>over them: Neither groſly to think, they cannot err, nor eaſily to think, they do. Keeps a mean between a blind Obedience, an implicite Faith: and betwixt a blind Diſobedience, a froward contemptuous reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of what a Congregation of God's People ſhall Decree. She has reſtored to the People, the one half of their Lord's Supper; the Blood, the Life of the Chriſtian Sacrifice; detained before by a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious Impropriation. Directs to diſcern the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Communion, from the corporal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſt; and from common Food: to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them with Reverence, but not with Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Renders into their Hands the Holy Scriptures; intercepted by the Roman See. Hides them not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Cover of a ſtrange Language; nor in the Cloſets of the Doctors: but ſets them on a Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick; that they which come in, may ſee the Light. Takes not from them the Word of God, leſt they ſhould miſenterpret it; but labours that they may not: Admoniſhes, Interprets, and Explains. Lets them underſtand their God, ſpeaking to them; and themſelves, ſpeaking to God: returns them their Prayers in their own Tongue: returns them I ſay. For neither was it thought fit, to depart from thoſe old Forms of Supplication, which God had been pleaſed to accept from Holy Men of the firſt Ages, which had been Conſecrated by the Mouths of the beſt Chriſtians; neither was it to be imagined, that God was to be pleaſed with the variety of a new Phraſe, or ſurpriſed by an extempore Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In like manner ſhe prayes not to Saints; but mentions their Names with Honour: uſes not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57271:11"/>the interceſſion of their Merits; but thanks God, for their Example. And as the Subſtance of our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is not oppreſſed and overcharged with Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Circumſtance; ſo neither is it left neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and unattended: We wait upon our God, with the whole Man; in compoſure of Mind and Body.</p>
            <p>And thus has the Engliſh Church rendered to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one their own: purged from Superſtition, and free from Novelty; reformed from Abuſe and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption on all Hands; it deſervedly takes place of thoſe of the laſt Ages; and may be ranked with the firſt, and beſt Centuries. The primitive Chriſtians, if they could be ſuppoſed to return upon the Earth, would profeſs our Faith; for it is theirs: and would certainly be of our Communion, for here they would find their own Doctrine, and their own Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. An Univerſal Infallible Biſhop, they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been acquainted with: and, of a Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Biſhop, they had never heard.</p>
            <p>So ſtands our Church, upon a Rock; beaten upon by Waves on all ſides: and, were the ſtrength of its Adverſaries, only in their Arguments; ſecure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. It ſtands firm, and upright: leans on nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide; and by its Frame, is in no danger of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. But the Malice of its Enemies is reſtleſs: they aſſault openly, and privately undermine; no way left unattempted; not by Men above, nor by Hell beneath: if they can't throw down; they blow up.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:57271:11"/>
            <p>And, amidſt all the Antichriſtian Variety of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, which the Contrivance of thoſe of <hi>Rome</hi> has deſigned againſt this Church and Nation; None, ſo unlikely to be prevented, ſo ſure and ſpeedy in the Execution, ſo like themſelves, and of ſo Catholick a Deſtruction, as that of this Day. When the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of a Monk, applied by the Malice of a Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite, had well nigh gratified their Roman Maſter, with the Wiſh, of one of his Heathen Predeceſſors, another vice-God; and diſpatcht a Nation, at a Blow. Neither have we had any Reaſon to think, that the ſame ſort of Men, are now more quiet, or grown more Merciful: their frequent Diſappointments may have only enraged them; and the memory of this Day they are to blot out, with the ſucceſs of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>They have always acted, with the greateſt Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence againſt this Kingdom, and againſt this Church: and for the ſame reaſon. Our Country, for it's na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Strength, great Riches, and Courage of its Inhabitants, is the firmeſt Support of the other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants: and, as ſoon as this Iſland were reduced; the Conqueſt of the other Hereticks, as they call us, might be eaſie; weak as they are, and divided. With the ſame Proſpect are their Deſigns, within this Kingdom, levell'd againſt our Church, as it ſtands here eſtabliſhed. That is their great, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Enemy. A Church regularly founded, by full Authority, Temporal, and Spiritual; not tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly Collected. Its Doctrine bottomed on the ſure Baſis of the Scripture; Apoſtolical in its Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and its Miniſters; having on its ſide, all that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57271:12"/>true Antiquity, which they themſelves vainly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend. A Church they are not able to reproach, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Novelty, or Sedition: whoſe Learning has been eminent to their Confuſion; and whoſe Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, by the Grace of God, has yet been well enough United, to withſtand their continued Attempts: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Body, and this Conſtitution, they direct all their Aim: apply their open Force, and their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Practices. This (which God forbid) if they ſhould ruine; they may think, it would be no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult thing, to deſtroy the other ill grounded, diſuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Societies that are among us, ty'd together by no Government, conſenting in no form of Doctrine, met together upon Fancy and Humour, holding they know not what, and agreeing they know not how.</p>
            <p>Neither are they ſo barren of miſchievous Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to be at a loſs if Poiſon, Dagger, or Powder fails: they can work on other Mines; and lay other Traines, than thoſe of this Day. It is indifferent to them, by what ſort of Artifice, the Frame of our Government flies aſunder: what it is, that Tears, and Rends, and breaks in pieces our Church and State: whether the matter, that is to ſcatter us, be under the places of our Aſſemblies, or in them: whether Houſes are burned by their Wildfire; or Mens Minds inflamed, and our Cities in a more dangerous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion: whether our Religion be ruin'd by them; or by their friends, Debauchees, Atheiſts, or Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſts. They thankfully accept the Pains, thoſe of the Separation take to divide and diſtract us: the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Preſent they make, of our whole Church into
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57271:12"/>their Boſom: contentedly allow all their Clamour againſt Popery, if they will but ſerve them ſo far, as to faſten that odious Popery upon us: glad to ſee the Papal Deſigns executed, at the Expence and Scandal, of thoſe that bear a Proteſtant Name: to ſee their Brethren of the Recuſancy as vigilant and vigorous at it, as if they were ſome new Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Popes, and had a General at <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo well agreed, that we are never in more Danger from the one, than when we are threatned by the other: Then our Church is not capacious enough, and ſhould be rebuilt, ſay thoſe that would pull it down; then its Gates are not broad enough, and Breaches to be made, wide enough for an Enemy to come in. On this ſide the Papiſt Mines, on that the Diſſenter Countermines: till by both the Foundation is ſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and the Fabrick ſinks. Our growing Schiſms giving our common Enemy certain Hopes of our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Ruine; and furniſhing them now with the beſt Argument, for a Head of Unity, and an Infallible Judge.</p>
            <p>Other Plots and Deſigns, which thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may have, it may not be in the Power of private Perſons to encounter: To oppoſe them there, may be the Work of other Hands; and the proper Buſineſs of Authority; (for we are to give to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> what is <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s.) But to oppoſe their moſt dangerous Deſigns, and that without which no other can prevail, that is in our own Power. It is every particular Man that is to hinder his being diſunited; to prevent and diſappoint the Advantages expected from our Diviſions. And to exhort and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57271:13"/>beſeech Men to lay aſide private Animoſities, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous and fanciful Diſtaſts, in matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; to keep the Unity of the Spirit, in the Bond of Peace; is a fit and neceſſary Duty at all times, in an Age that wants Charity ſo much, and has ſo little of Chriſtian Condeſcenſion: but at this time more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently ſeaſonable, and abſolutely neceſſary. To agree now in the Service of God, as it is the Duty of each in private; ſo it is the Intereſt of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. The Houſe of God its ſelf, if divided againſt it ſelf, cannot ſtand. Whatever other Inſtruments of our Ruine, thoſe of <hi>Rome</hi> may have; let no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant ſuffer his Zeal to be made one.</p>
            <p>To be truly oppoſite to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to prevent their future Deſigns, and in gratitude for our paſt Deliverances; let us, in obedience to the direction of the Text, and in imitation of our Church, render to every one their Due. To the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church, that juſt and thankful Teſtimony, that nothing can be more contrary to the Falſhoods, Uſurpations, and Corruptions of the Romiſh See: nothing more agreeable to the Peace, good Order, and Government of the Kingdom. In the head of this Church, to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> what is <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s; a grateful loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Reſentment of the great Bleſſings, we enjoy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Gracious Government: no half-Subjection nor Popiſh Conformity to his Laws; an Obedience, clear of Roman Shifts, and Jeſuitical Evaſions: not ſetting up a private Antipapal Authority, to abſolve our ſelves in ſome caſes, from our Allegiance; and deny his Majeſtie's Supremacy, in favour of our own.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:57271:13"/>
            <p>To God, particularly on this Occaſion, all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Thanks, and Acknowledgment. That he was firſt pleaſed to ſhine early upon this Nation, in the returning Light of the Goſpel, the Doctrine of the Reformation: diſcovering to us, as it were by a new Revelation, his true Religion, freed from the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and Impoſtures of Men; from a Burden of Ceremonies, almoſt Jewiſh; and an Idolatry, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Pagan. That he was pleaſed, during the Reign of the ſucceeding Princeſs, to continue this his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Gift to us; to the Confuſion of all the Enemies of our Faith, and Countrey, both at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. And particularly under her Succeſſor King, that the Divine Majeſty was pleaſed, by a ſingular extraordinary Providence, to diſappoint a Treaſon, unexampled in its Malice, and of an unheard Deſign: The Prince of Darkneſs himſelf contriving and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring the horrid Plot beneath; God watching from above, and confounding the accurſed Work, by a Miracle almoſt as great, as if the Train had took, and he had ſtopt the Blow: that he has been pleaſed ſince ſtill to defeat, by a conſtant jealous Care, the reſtleſs Enemies of our Peace and Religion; preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from their Malice and Treachery that Sacred Head, next and immediate under God, our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Defendor: preſerving us all to his true Worſhip, from Confuſion and War: whoſe Grace it is, that we aſſemble, as at this time, in Peace and Safety; worſhip him, as here, in Purity.</p>
            <p>Neither is this all, on this Occaſion, we owe our God: We are to continue our Thanks beyond the Day; and expreſs our ſelves ſenſible of the Divine
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57271:14"/>Favour, by improving it to the moſt Advantage. We ſtand ſtill obliged to a farther Juſtice, to give our Proteſtant Religion its Due, and let It have its proper bleſſed Effects.</p>
            <p>That the Purity and Reformation of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be not only read in our Articles, and Liturgy; and thoſe framed by the Piety of our Anceſtors: but ſeen on our own Perſons, exemplified in our Lives. That our Worſhip of God, diſcover by the Intenſeneſs of the Devotion; that it is not diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any other Object, nor diverted on Saints and Angels. That it appear not, by our ſlackneſs at the Holy Communion; that we could have been without the Uſe of Both Kinds. That it be viſible, by our zealous attention to our Prayers; that we Underſtand them: and, by our Obedience to God's Word; that we have Read it: not from impious Alluſions, and ſuch Profanations; as may almoſt juſtifie the Papal Prohibition. Let us ſhew, by the frequency of our own Charities, and Devotions, now; that we think thoſe of Others for us, after our Death, of no avail: by our abhorrence of all Sin; that we account none Venial: and, by the religious Careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Lives, that we truſt not to Indulgences, or eaſie Abſolutions. They, that doubt of a Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of Salvation for thoſe of the Other Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, in This, let them ſecure their own: and, while we profeſs, by good Works we cannot Merit Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; let us not, by bad, Deſerve a greater Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the proper<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Teſts of a true Proteſtant; and ſigns of a holy Zeal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Other noiſy Clamours,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57271:14"/>and angry Heats againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> have no more of Religion in them; than is in the loud ſounds on that occaſion we hear from the tops of our Churches; or in the Fire, that burns in the Streets. If we would intirely baniſh Popery; let none of its Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption be retained in our Manners; let our Lives, and our Converſations Proteſt. So ſhall we beſt thank God for the Mercy of this Day; and engage his Protection for the future.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
